taking personal responsibility for our
health is one of the most important
things we can do regular exercise not
smoking and eating a healthy diet can
help prevent and even reverse some of
the most common diseases and
most people know this so why don't they
eat healthier watch the video to find
out
[Music]
yes media messages surrounding nutrition
are often inconsistent and confusing but
many americans know what constitutes a
healthy diet i mean does anyone really
think drinking brown carbonated sugar
water is good for them
at issue is that they don't appear to be
translating their knowledge into action
there are a number of reasons people
have such difficulty changing their
dietary behaviors while ignorance and
confusion may play a part the motivation
to change is likely much more important
certainly we are living in a world that
pushes us to eat whatever we want
regardless of the long-term consequences
but one of the major problems in getting
people to change their behavior is the
need to get them to recognize the need
to change for example if you ask people
how much meat they eat or how much
greasy food eggs sweets alcohol butter
they claim to be eating less than the
average person
so if people think they're at less risk
than others
they may dismiss advice to eat more
healthfully thinking that they already
eat healthier
maybe they are
no
people rated their own eating behavior
as healthier on average even when their
actual eating habits were terrible
for this reason maybe health-promoting
campaigns need to make people aware of
how badly they're eating but when you do
that a strange thing happens if you
challenge people with the reality of
what the average person actually eats
they change their answer to make
themselves appear as though they're
still healthier than average
when people's favorable comparisons on
risky behaviors are threatened they not
only reduce their estimates of how often
they engage in those behaviors oh i
don't eat that much meat
but they also attenuate the significance
of those behaviors meat's not that bad
for you anyway
it's the same personal fable that
smokers tell themselves a studies show
that smokers have a strong tendency to
underestimate all smoking-related risks
developing a series of illusions and
false beliefs to support their choice to
keep on smoking
why do so many people continue to light
up in spite of smoking's harmful effects
to their health
for many of the same reasons people
continue to eat unhealthy food first
they convince themselves that they are
less at risk than others who engage in
the same behavior
and in addition to this optimism bias
smokers underestimate the extent to
which smoking elevates lung cancer risk
thinking two pack-a-day smokers only
have like five times the risk of getting
lung cancer when their actual risk is
20-fold higher
and anyway many smokers believe lung
cancer is mainly determined by one's
genes many food-related hazards share
the same optimistic bias such as heart
attacks and heart disease our number one
killer obesity diabetes and all the rest
people are often quite ingenious and
finding reasons for believing that their
own risk is less than the risk faced by
their peers
so maybe public health advocates need to
be just as ingenious in understanding
the origins of this unrealistic optimism
and in finding approaches to help people
gain a more accurate picture of their
own vulnerability
all sorts of work is being done trying
to reduce or eliminate this bias
but we must consider the possibility
that reductions in optimistic bias
may lead to reductions in self-esteem
and psychological well-being if people
start to realize just how much risk they
truly face and how much they have
themselves to blame
this reminds me of the tightrope wire
health professionals have to walk
telling people how much power we all
have over getting cancer
this is the off-sided paper that
calculated that we may be able to
prevent approximately 90 percent of
human cancers but by
present trends the researchers talking
about present trends of the 1960s when
the paper was published
they remained true to this day though
about a half century later genetic
factors are not the major causes of
chronic diseases using identical twins
to see how much was really just in your
genes of all the chronic diseases they
looked at
cancers had the lowest genetic component
again only about 10 percent attributable
to bad genes what runs in families is
bad
habits
but when you go out there and tell
everyone the good news about how much
power we have over not getting cancer
what about the people who already have
it when people are diagnosed with cancer
they often ask why me did i do something
wrong is this my fault so you can
imagine how the message of
well yeah
kinda
could be destructive for patients or
survivors
in other words a message that is
intended to empower people in a
prevention context
could just make cancer victims feel
guilty
but the truth is still the truth no
matter how difficult it may be so what
we have to do is try to guide patients
to switch from feelings of guilt to a
responsibility approach they have
personal control they can make different
choices from then on we need to give
them a sense of agency in their life
better though to try to take those steps
before you get cancer
[Music]
you